A Guide to the Barringer Family Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Barringer Family Papers ca. 1812-1966
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2588, -a, -b, -c, -d, -e, -g
This collection consists of ca. 3000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Barringer Family Papers were given to the Library by various members of the Barringer family between 1937 and 1981.
Scope and Content
The Barringer Family Papers comprise ca. 2,830 items (twelve Hollinger boxes and 1 oversize folder, 5.2 linear shelf feet), 1828-1963, consisting of correspondence, legal and financial documents, literary manuscripts, genealogical material, newsclippings, photographs and keepsake items, certificates and commissions, printed articles and pamphlets, monographs and broadsides. These papers pertain chiefly to Paul Brandon Barringer (1857-1941) and other members of his family, most notably General Rufus Barringer (1821-1895) and Victor C. Barringer (1828-1896). A few of these papers also pertain to T. J. "Stonewall" Jackson and his wife, Anna Morrison Jackson who were related to the Barringer family by marriage. Additional genealogical data exist for the following families: Brandon, Graham, Hannah, Massey, Morrison, Spragins, Washington, and Woodson.
The bulk of the Barringer material consists of the personal papers of Paul Brandon Barringer professor of medicine and chairman of the faculty of the University of Virginia founder of the University of Virginia Hospital president of the Agricultural and Mechanical College of Virginia (presently Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University), a member of the Virginia Board of Health and Virginia Board of Agriculture an inventor, and author on topics varying from family history to racial affairs. Little of this material illuminates his professional life with the exception of those documents associated with his tenure at Virginia Polytechnic Institute. The chief focus of his papers is social and intellectual.
Most of the correspondence in these papers deals with Barringer family affairs and personal matters concerning Paul B. Barringer. Topics include family illness, real estate dealings and other financial matters, speaking engagements, the American Negro, and occasionally, politics (especially Barringer's unsuccessful attempt to be appointed United States Secretary of Agriculture). Among the correspondents are: Edwin A. Alderman Harry F. Byrd John Armstrong Chaloner Lenoir Chambers William A. Clark Hugh S. Cumming Charles W. Dabney John Dalzell Josephus Daniels Noah K. Davis R. T. W. Duke E. C. Glass Carter Glass Armistead C. Gordon Hugh S. Johnson Fitzhugh Lee Andrew J. Montague R. Walton Moore John L. Newcomb Robert C. Ogden Lee S. Overman Thomas N. Page Thomas W. Page William L. Phelps John F. Rixey Albert Shaw C. Alphonso Smith Claude A. Swanson Benjamin R. Tillman J. Hoge Tyler Oscar W. Underwood Henry A. Wallace and John Sharp Williams. Among those corresponding with Paul B. Barringer concerning racial matters are: Lyman Abbott Frank P. Brent John W. Daniel H. B. Frissell Armistead C. Gordon Thomas W. Harrison Hilary A. Herbert Edgar G. Murphy Clarence Poe Charles D. Warner and Booker T. Washington. Additional correspondence includes editorial letters written by Paul B. Barringer which discuss political, civic and social issues. A small group of letters (11 items) contains typed and autograph documents by President Theodore Roosevelt chiefly concerning his visit to the University of Virginia in 1903.
Correspondence from the nineteenth century also includes letters by Daniel Laurens Barringer (Congressman, North Carolina), Daniel Moreau Barringer (Congressman, North Carolina; Minister to Spain), T. J. "Stonewall" Jackson (photocopies) and his wife, Anna (Morrison) Jackson and General Rufus Barringer who offers a detailed account of life as a Confederate prisoner of war at Fort Delaware, Delaware (ALS-Photostat). Other occasional references to Civil War news (especially during 1863) and to the sale, price and investment value of slaves also appear in some of these early letters. Letters dated from the 1870's include accounts of boarding school life (Bingham School, Mebaneville, North Carolina; Kenmore University School, Amherst Court House, Virginia; A. F. Seminary, Staunton, Virginia) by Paul B. Barringer and Anna Barringer.
An important group of correspondence and related papers documents a series of investigations stemming from charges made by the Virginia Polytechnic Institute Alumni Association Welfare Committee against Paul B. Barringer while he was president of Virginia Polytechnic Institute (1907-1913). Included in these documents are newsclippings, affidavits, evidentiary exhibits, copies of formal charges and Barringer's replies to them, and printed matter regarding the investigation. An additional set of documents concerns charges made against R. J. Noell of the Radford State Normal School by the Radford Record (1913).
The Barringer Family Papers also contain autograph and typescript notes and literary drafts, as well as printed articles and monographs, written chiefly either by or about Paul B. Barringer. Included are essays, memoirs and several printed monographs by Barringer, but most of the material comprises note and draft fragments. Anthropology, race, religion and theology are the predominant topics in these writings. Other subjects, including economics, history, medicine, prohibition and biography, are also represented. Additional authors include General Rufus Barringer and Daniel Moreau Barringer.
A separate group of documents (104 items) contains drawings, legal papers, printed specifications and patent certificates ( United States of America Canada Great Britain) for a fire extinguisher which Paul B. Barringer invented.
Among the miscellaneous items within these papers are documents referring to the University of Virginia Michel Ney (Marshal of France) (1769-1815), and Georgia O'Keeffe (1887-). Miscellaneous financial documents include receipts of Victor C. Barringer General Rufus Barringer and Paul B. Barringer accounts from Paul B. Barringer 's ophthalmology practice, canceled checks, and bank statements and utility accounts compiled during Paul B. Barringer 's tenure at Virginia Polytechnic Institute Certificates commissions and licences (many oversize) awarded to Paul B. Barringer and Nannie (Hannah) Barringer include his license to practice medicine in Virginia (1890). Engravings and numerous photographs depict various family members and " Gravel Hill " a home in Charlotte County, Virginia.
In addition, these papers contain numerous newsclippings pertaining to the Barringer and Morrison families in Virginia and North Carolina and three theater broadsides featuring Edwin Booth in leading roles. Bound volumes, which include a commonplace book of General Rufus Barringer Paul B. Barringer 's case book, and a scrapbook of newsclippings pertaining to the "Negro question," are also included.
Photographs of interest include Robert E. Lee with former Confederate generals at White Sulphur Springs, 1869 and Dr. Paul Barringer and Dr. William Mann Randolph in a buggy at "the Corner," 1906.
Organization
The Barringer Family Papers are arranged in eight series: I. General Correspondence; II. Virginia Polytechnic Institute Papers; III. Fire Extinguisher Papers; IV. Literary Manuscripts; V. Genealogical Material; VI.Printed Material; VII. Miscellaneous; VIII. Bound Volumes. These series are ordered chronologically with two exceptions: Series IV. Literary Manuscripts, which is arranged alphabetically by fragment topics and essay titles; Series V. Genealogical Material, which is arranged alphabetically by family name. Most letters have been filed under Series I. General Correspondence. However, letters pertaining exclusively to Barringer's tenure at Virginia Polytechnic Institute to his fire extinguisher patents, or to genealogical topics, have been placed in those respective series.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1828-1914; 6 folders (Box Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1915-1963, n. d.; 3 folders (Box Box 2)
  - Correspondence, chiefly regarding President Theodore Roosevelt's visit to UVa, 1903-1909; TLS, ALS (Box Box 2)
  - Editorial Letters from Paul Brandon Barringer, 1909-1910, n. d. (Box Box 2)
- Series II: V. P. I. Papers
  - General Correspondence and related papers regarding Paul Brandon Barringer at V. P. I., 1906-1910; 2 folders (Box Box 2)
  - General Correspondence and related papers regarding Paul Brandon Barringer at V. P. I., 1911-1913, n. d.; 2 folders (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence regarding Walter J. Quick, Dean of Agriculture Department, V. P. I., 1907-1909 (Box Box 3)
  - Correspondence and related papers regarding charges against Paul B. Barringer made by the V. P. I. Alumni Association Welfare Committee, 1910; 2 folders (Box Box 3)
  - Evidentiary exhibits regarding 1910 investigation (Box Box 3)
  - Evidentiary exhibits regarding 1910 investigation (Box Box 4)
  - "Investigation of Charges of the Welfare Committee..." (V. P. I. Alum. Assoc.) vs Paul B. Barringer: transcript of proceedings before the board of Visitors of V. P. I., 1910 Mar 25-26; TD (carbon) (Box Box 4)
  - Paul B. Barringer's response to charges made by the Welfare Committee (V. P. I.), w/additional notes, 1910 Mar 25; TD (Box Box 4)
  - Printed matter regarding investigation of 1910 (Box Box 4)
  - Affidavits and other documents regarding investigation of 1911 (Box Box 4)
  - Paul B. Barringer's reply to charges preferred against him by Mr. Kline, 1911 (Box Box 4)
  - Newsclippings regarding Paul B. Barringer's tenure as president of V. P. I., 1907-1913, n. d. (Box Box 5)
  - Correspondence, clippings and printed matter regarding Radford State Normal/R. J. Noell investigation, 1913 (Box Box 5)
- Series III: Fire Extinguisher Papers
  - Correspondence regarding fire extinguisher, 1909-1918, n. d. (Box Box 5)
  - Drawings, legal papers and printed specifications regarding fire extinguishers, 1881-1915, n. d. (Box Box 5)
  - Fire extinguisher patents: U. S. A., Canada, and Great Britain, 1911-1915, n. d. (Box Box 5)
- Series IV: Literary Manuscripts
  - Addresses given by Paul B. Barringer, 1908-1938, n. d. (Box Box 6)
  - Addresses given by others, 1933-1935 (Box Box 6)
  - Essays on theology, religion and anthropology, 1923, n. d.; 3 folders (Box Box 6)
  - Medical topics, n. d. (Box Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous essays: fiction, history, economics, etc., n. d. (Box Box 6)
  - Race relations, 1911-1912, n. d. (Box Box 7)
  - Poetry, 1925 (Box Box 7)
  - Prohibition, 1924, n. d. (Box Box 7)
  - "The Autobiography of a Post-bellum Boy," w/corrections, n. d.; TMsS 2 drafts (Box Box 7)
  - "The Evolution of Sex: Body and Soul" (incomplete), w/corrections, TMs (Box Box 7)
  - "The Faith Fundamental," w/notes, TMs, AMs (Box Box 7)
  - "The Faith Fundamental", TMs, AMs (Box Box 8)
  - ["Memoirs of Dr. Paul Barringer"] early draft w/ corrections, n. d.; TMs (Box Box 8)
  - "Memoirs of Dr. Paul Brandon Barringer," volumes 1 and 2, edited by Anna Barringer, w/corrections, TMs (2 folders) (Box Box 8)
  - "The Moses of the Medians," w/corrections, ca. 1923; TMs (Box Box 8)
  - "Primal Theology," including notes, draft fragments, w/corrections, n. d.; TMs, AN (Box Box 8)
  - "A Primer of Prehistory", n. d.; TMs (Box Box 8)
  - "The Quest", n. d.; TMs (Box Box 9)
  - "Reminiscences of Doctor Paul B. Barringer", n. d.; TMs (Box Box 9)
- Series V: Genealogical Material
  - Barringer Genealogy and Family history, 1812, 1867-1959, n. d. (Box Box 9)
  - Brandon Genealogy, 1925-1958, n. d. (Box Box 9)
  - Hannah Genealogy, 1901, 1958, n. d. (Box Box 9)
  - Massey Genealogy, 1944-1956 (Box Box 9)
  - Morrison Genealogy, including papers regarding T. J. "Stonewall" Jackson, 1816, 1849, 1921-1958, n. d. (Box Box 9)
  - Washington Genealogy, n. d. (Box Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous genealogies: Graham, Spragins, Woodson et. al., 1944-1959, n. d. (Box Box 9)
  - Biographical data regarding John Paul Barringer, 1909, 1942, n. d. (Box Box 10)
  - Biographical data regarding Paul Brandon Barringer, [1872-1941] 1961, n. d. (Box Box 10)
  - Biographical data regarding General Rufus Barringer, [1875-1901] 1961, n. d. (Box Box 10)
  - Biographical data regarding Victor C. Barringer, 1865, 1896, 1945-1956 (Box Box 10)
- Series VI: Printed Material
  - Printed material, 1880-1949, n. d.; 2 folders (Box Box 10)
  - Printed material regarding race relations, 1896-1925, n. d. (Box Box 10)
  - Theater Broadsides, 1865-1889 (Box Box 11)
  - Newsclippings, 1889-1964, n. d. (Box Box 11)
- Series VII: Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous, 1875-1966, n. d. (Box Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous financial papers, 1848, 1881-1927 (Box Box 11)
  - Certificates, commissions, licenses, 1893-1942, n. d. (Box Box 11)
  - Engravings, photos, keepsake items, 1859-1949, n. d. (Box Box 11)
- Series VIII: Bound Volumes
  - Commonplace book of General Rufus Barringer (electrostatic copy), ca. 1880 (Box Box 12)
  - Case Book of Dr. Paul B. Barringer, 1891-1897 (Box Box 12)
  - Business Ledger, 1901-1902 (Box Box 12)
  - Scrapbook of newsclippings regarding race relations, ca. 1901-1904 (Box Box 12)
- Oversize
  - Graduate diploma, University of Virginia, School of analytical and Agricultural Chemistry, Paul Brandon Barringer, 1876 Jun 29
  - Graduate diploma, University of Virginia, School of General and Industrial Chemistry, Paul B. Barringer, 1876 Jun 29
  - Graduate Diploma, University of Virginia, School of Natural History and Agriculture, Paul B. Barringer, 1876 Jun 29
  - United States Passport of Paul B. Barringer, 1881 Mar 3
  - Diploma, Charlotte Female Institute, Nannie Hannah, 1882 Jun 7
  - License to practice medicine, State of Virginia, Paul B. Barringer, 1890 Apr 11
  - Certificate of membership, Daughters of the American Revolution, Nannie Hannah Barringer, 1893 Feb 16
  - Certificate of achievement, Men of Mark in America-State of Virginia., Paul B. Barringer, 1904 Dec 13
  - Honorary Doctor of Laws diploma, South Carolina College, Paul B. Barringer, 1905 Jan 10
  - Photograph of members of the Virginia Medical Association, Mecklenburg, November 13-16, 1907, [ca. 1907 Nov 13-16]
  - Commission as delegate, Farmers National Congress, Paul B. Barringer, 1909 Aug 16
  - Commission as representative, Southern Commercial Congress, Paul B. Barringer, 1912 Apr 1
  - Bachelor of Science (Teaching) diploma, Columbia University, Anna Marie Barringer, 1914 Jun 3
  - Bachelor of Science (Fine Arts) diploma, Columbia University, Anna M. Barringer, 1914 Jun 3
  - Commission as delegate, National Association of Conservation, Paul B. Barringer, 1914 Nov 11
  - Bachelor of Arts diploma, Hollins College, Eugenia Morrison Barringer, 1915 Jun 2
  - Certificate of membership, Daughters of the American Revolution, Anna M. Barringer, 1917 Jan 17
  - High School diploma, Public High School, Charlottesville, Virginia, John Hannah Barringer, 1919 Jun 13
  - Certificate of membership, Alpha Omega Alpha (medical honorary), Paul B. Barringer, 1922
  - Certificate of membership, Sons of the American Revolution, Paul B. Barringer, 1923 Jun 7
  - Bachelor of Science diploma, University of Virginia, John Hannah Barringer, 1924 Jun 10
  - Chicago Sunday Tribune, pages 1 and 2, with article "Vivid Stories Told of Jefferson", 1931 Dec 20
  - Certificate of membership, Alumni Association of the University of Virginia, Paul B. Barringer, 1938 Jun 11